Ichthyology,
علم الأسماك،
the study of fishes.
علم دراسة الأسماك،
It looks like a big, boring word,
تبدو كلمة ثقيلة ومملة،
but it's actually quite exciting,
لكنها في الحقيقة مثيرة للغاية،
because ichthyology is the only "ology"
لأن علم الأسماك هو "فرع المعرفة" الوحيد
with "YOLO" in it.
الذي يحوي "YOLO".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, to the cool kids in the audience,
الآن، بالنسبة للأطفال بين الجمهور،
you already know, YOLO stands for "you only live once,"
تعلمون أن YOLO هي اختصار "أنتم تعيشون مرة واحدة فقط،"
and because I only have one life,
ولأنني أعيش حياة واحدة،
I'm going to spend it doing what I always dreamt of doing:
فسأقضيها في عمل ما كنتُ دائماً أحلم بالقيام به:
seeing the hidden wonders of the world and discovering new species.
رؤية عجائب الدنيا الخفية واستكشاف مخلوقات جديدة.
And that's what I get to do.
وهذا هو ما أقوم به.
Now, in recent years, I really focused on caves for finding new species.
الآن،وفي السنوات الأخيرة، ركزتُ على الكهوف للعثور على مخلوقات جديدة.
And it turns out, there's lots of new cavefish species out there.
وتبين أن هناك الكثير من أنواع الأسماك الكهفية الحديثة.
You just have to know where to look,
عليكم معرفة أين تفتشون فقط،
and to maybe be a little thin.
وربما عليكم أن تكونوا أكثر رشاقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, cavefishes can tell me a lot about biology and geology.
حالياً، يمكن لأسماك الكهوف أن تخبرنا عن الكائنات الحية/بيولوجيا، والأرض/جيولوجيا.
They can tell me how the landmasses around them have changed and moved
يمكنها أن تخبرني كيف أن اليابسة حولها قد تغيرت وتحركت
by being stuck in these little holes,
عن طريق بقائها عالقة في مثل هذه الثقوب الصغيرة،
and they can tell me about the evolution of sight, by being blind.
ويمكنها أن تخبرني أيضاً عن تطور البصر عن طريق كونها عمياء.
Now, fish have eyes that are essentially the same as ours.
لدى الأسماك عيون هي في الأساس مثل أعيننا.
All vertebrates do, and each time a fish species starts to adapt
لدى كل الفقاريات عيون، وفي كل مرة تبداُ المخلوقات السمكية في التكيف
to this dark, cold, cave environment,
لبيئة الكهف الباردة والمظلمة،
over many, many generations, they lose their eyes and their eyesight
على مدى العديد والعديد من الأجيال، فإنها تفقدُ أعينها وبصرها
until the end up like an eyeless cavefish like this one here.
حتى ينتهي الأمر بمثل هذه السمكة الكهفية بلا عيون.
Now, each cavefish species has evolved in a slightly different way,
حالياً، تطورت كل أنواع الأسماك الكهفية بطريقة مختلفة قليلاً،
and each one has a unique geological and biological story to tell us,
ولدى كل واحدة قصة جيولوجية وبيولوجية لتخبرنا عنها،
and that's why it's so exciting when we find a new species.
ولهذا السبب فإنه لمن المثير عندما نعثرُ على مخلوقات جديدة.
So this is a new species we described, from southern Indiana.
هذه هي مخلوقات جديدة أعلنا عنها من جنوب ولاية إنديانا.
We named it Amblyopsis hoosieri, the Hoosier cavefish.
أطلقنا عليها إسم "أمبليوسيس هوزيراي"، سمكة الكهف هوزير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Its closest relatives are cavefishes in Kentucky,
وأقرب أقارب لها هم أسماك الكهوف في ولاية كنتاكي،
in the Mammoth Cave system.
في نظام كهف الماموث.
And they start to diverge when the Ohio River split them
وشرعوا في الابتعاد عندما فصلهم نهر أوهايو
a few million years ago.
قبل بضعة ملاييين من السنين.
And in that time they developed these subtle differences
وطوّروا عندئذٍ هذه الفروقات الطفيفة
in the genetic architecture behind their blindness.
في الهندسة الجينية الوراثية وراء العمى الذي أصابهم.
There's this gene called rhodopsin that's super-critical for sight.
يطلقُ على هذا الجين رودوبسين و هو شديد الحساسية للبصر.
We have it, and these species have it too,
موجود لدينا ولدى هذه المخلوقات أيضاً.
except one species has lost all function in that gene,
عدا مخلوقات واحدة التي فقدت جميع وظائف هذا الجين،
and the other one maintains it.
وحافظت أخرى عليه.
So this sets up this beautiful natural experiment
لذلك فهو يشكل هذه التجربة الطبيعية الجميلة
where we can look at the genes behind our vision,
حيثُ يمكننا النظر في الجينات فيما وراء حاسة البصر لدينا،
and at the very roots of how we can see.
وإلى حدٍ بعيد في جذور الطريقة التي نرى بها.
But the genes in these cavefishes
لكن يمكن الجينات في الأسماك الكهفية
can also tell us about deep geological time,
أن تخبرنا عن الزمن العميق الغامض للأرض،
maybe no more so than in this species here.
ربما ليس أكثر من هذ المخلوقات هنا.
This is a new species we described from Madagascar
هذه هي مخلوقات جديدة وصفناها من مدغشقر
that we named Typhleotris mararybe.
والتي أطلقنا عليها اسم "تيفليوتريس ماراريبي."
That means "big sickness" in Malagasy,
وتعني "المرض الكبير" في اللغة الملغاشية،
for how sick we got trying to collect this species.
حيث أننا سئمنا ونحنُ نحاول جمع هذه المخلوقات.
Now, believe it or not,
الآن، صدقوا أو لا تصدقوا،
swimming around sinkholes full of dead things
فالسباحة حول المجاري المليئة بالأشياء الميتة
and cave full of bat poop
والكهف المليء بفضلات الخفافيش
isn't the smartest thing you could be doing with your life,
ليس بالأمر العاقل الذي يمكنكم القيام به بحياتكم.
but YOLO.
لكنكم تعيشون مرة واحدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I love this species despite the fact that it tried to kill us,
أحبُ هذه المخلوقات على الرغم أنها حاولت قتلنا في الواقع،
and that's because this species in Madagascar,
ولأن هذا النوع من الكائنات الحية يعيش في مدغشقر،
its closest relatives are 6,000 kilometers away,
أقرب المقربين لها هم على بعد 6،000 كيلومتر،
cavefishes in Australia.
أسماك الكهوف في أستراليا.
Now, there's no way a three-inch-long freshwater cavefish
الآن، لا يوجد طريقة لسمكة كهفية طولها ثلاثة إنشات وتعيش في مياه عذبة
can swim across the Indian Ocean,
يمكنُ لها أن تسبح عبر المحيط الهندي،
so what we found when we compared the DNA of these species
فما وجدناه عندما قارنا الحمض النووي لهذه المخلوقات الحية
is that they've been separated for more than 100 million years,
هو أنه تم فصلها منذ أكثر من 100 مليون سنة،
or about the time that the southern continents were last together.
أو في الحقبة الزمنية التي كانت فيه القارات الجنوبية ملتصقة معاً.
So in fact, these species didn't move at all.
في الحقيقة، لم تنتقل هذه المخلوقات على الإطلاق.
It's the continents that moved them.
القارات هي التي حركتهم ونقلتهم.
And so they give us, through their DNA,
وأعطتنا من خلال الحمض النووي لديها،
this precise model and measure
هذا المقياس والنموذج الدقيق
of how to date and time these ancient geological events.
لكيفية تاريخ ووقت هذه الأحداث الجيولوجية القديمة.
Now, this species here is so new
حالياً، هذه الأنواع من المخلوقات هي جديدة جداً
I'm not even allowed to tell you its name yet,
وحتى الآن ليس مسموح لي حتى أن أخبركم باسمها،
but I can tell you it's a new species from Mexico,
لكن أستطيع أن أقول لكم أنها كائنات حية جديدة من المكسيك،
and it's probably already extinct.
وأنها ربما انقرضت فعلاً.
It's probably extinct because the only known cave system it's from
ربما انقرضت لأنها من نظام الكهف الوحيد المعروف
was destroyed when a dam was built nearby.
والذي تم تدميره عندما تم بناء سد بالقرب منه.
Unfortunately for cavefishes,
لسوء حظ الأسماك الكهفية،
their groundwater habitat
موطنها هو المياه الجوفية
is also our main source of drinking water.
التي هي أيضاً مصدرنا الرئيسي لشرب المياه.
Now, we actually don't know this species' closest relative, yet.
حالياً، لا نعرفُ في الحقيقة أقرب أقارب هذه المخلوقات بعد.
It doesn't appear to be anything else in Mexico,
ولا يبدو أنها مثل أي شيء آخر في المكسيك،
so maybe it's something in Cuba,
ربما تكون شيئا ما في كوبا،
or Florida, or India.
أو في فلوريدا، أو في الهند.
But whatever it is, it might tell us something new about the geology
ولكن أياً كان، فقد تخبرنا شيئاً جديداً حول جيولوجيا الأرض
of the Caribbean, or the biology of how to better diagnose
في جزر البحر الكاريبي، أو بيولوجيا الكائنات لتشخيص أفضل
certain types of blindness.
لأنواع محددة من العمى.
But I hope we discover this species before it goes extinct too.
ولكن آملُ أن نكتشف هذه الأنواع قبل انقراضها أيضاً.
And I'm going to spend my one life
وسأقضي حياتي كلها
as an ichthyologist trying to discover and save
كعالِم أسماك محاولاً اكتشاف وإنقاذ
these humble little blind cavefishes
هذه الأسماك الكهفية الصغيرة الوديعة العمياء
that can tell us so much about the geology of the planet
التي يمكنُ أن تخبرنا الكثير عن جيولوجيا كوكب الأرض
and the biology of how we see.
وبيولوجيا كيف نرى.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)